Guide to the James Cartoons Posters, 1920-1921 RL.00626
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
James Cartoons Posters
1920-1921
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
New Process Electro Corporation
RL.00626
3 Linear Feet
The New Process Electro Corporation was based in the Times Building, on Broadway at 42nd Street in New York City. Its president was Charles C. James, who also served as president of the James Investment Company (St. Louis, Mo.) and the Paramount Advertising Corporation. Dates and activities for this corporation are not known, other than it appears to have been active from at least 1913 through 1921, the date of this collection's latest cartoon. Collection of 14 political posters, 1920-1921, created as part of the James Cartoons series by the New Process Electro Corporation. Subjects include foreign policy, especially Europe and the League of Nations; the 1920 presidential election between Warren G. Harding and James M. Cox; and financial topics such as Germany's war debts, coal shortages, and the Ponzi scheme.
14 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The James Cartoons Posters were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2010.
Historical Note
The New Process Electro Corporation was based in the Times Building, on Broadway at 42nd Street in New York City. Its president was Charles C. James, who also served as president of the James Investment Company (St. Louis, Mo.) and the Paramount Advertising Corporation. Dates and operations for the New Process Electro Corporation are not known, other than it appears to have been active from at least 1913 through 1921, the date of this collection's latest cartoon.
Collection Overview
Collection of 14 political posters created as part of the James Cartoons series by the New Process Electro Corporation in New York. The posters, which appear to be by an anonymous artist, were originally part of a subscription available for $1.25 per week. The posters in this collection are all from Volume 7 of the series, dating from 1920-1921.
The posters are chromolithographs, each sized 21.5 x 31 inches. Their condition is good but fragile, as their fold lines and some marginal tears require careful handling.
Subjects include foreign policy, especially post-World War I Europe and U.S. attitudes towards the League of Nations; the 1920 presidential election between Warren G. Harding and James M. Cox; and financial topics such as Germany's war debts, coal shortages in the United States, and the Ponzi scheme. The artist uses caricatures to represent political figures or ideas; for example, the country of Russia is regularly shown as an angry bear, while Germany is a toothless dachsund. The election-themed posters often incorporate a donkey and an elephant representing each political party, usually accompanying the various candidates who are engaged in some sort of competition. The 14 poster titles have been captioned below, along with a brief description of the events being portrayed by the artist.
Collection Arrangement
Posters are arranged chronologically in two oversize folders.
Political cartoons -- United States; United States -- Caricatures and cartoons; James Cartoons; Presidents -- Elections -- Caricatures and cartoons; Ponzi, Charles -- Caricatures and cartoons; Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- ) -- Caricatures and cartoons; New Process Electro Corporation; New Process Electro Corporation; Harding, Warren G. -- Caricatures and cartoons; League of Nations -- Caricatures and cartoons; Cox, James M. (James Middleton), 1870-1957 -- Caricatures and cartoons; Democratic Party (U.S.) -- Caricatures and cartoons
- James Cartoons, 1920-1921, 2 folders
  - Try Your Luck Boys! Vol. 7, No. 8, dated 1920 (Oversize-folder 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    At a fair booth, the GOP elephant aims for targets representing the country's problems, including labor troubles, prohibition, and League of Nations disputes. Woodrow Wilson and the Democrat donkey watch.
  - Another Cup Race! Vol. 7, No. 9, dated 1920 (Oversize-folder 1)
    The Democrats and GOP sail away while the Third Party's sailboat loses its wind.
  - A Puzzling Situation! Vol. 7, No. 10, dated 1920 (Oversize-folder 1)
    Russia (an angry bear) heads towards Germany (a dachsund on a leash) while other European countries look on.
  - Up A Tree! Vol. 7, No. 11, dated 1920 (Oversize-folder 1)
    Russia (an angry bear) tries to chase Poland (a farmer), who is trapped at the top of a tree. Other European powers roll a Blockade (a boulder) in front of the tree.
  - Ponzi the Great! Vol. 7, No. 12, dated 1920 (Oversize-folder 1)
    At his magic show, Ponzi the magician is hauled offstage by Uncle Sam.
  - How Times Have Changed. Vol. 7, No. 14, dated 1920 (Oversize-folder 1)
    Lower classes enjoy chauffered rides and fancy clothes while America's richest citizens stand in line.
  - A Hornet's Nest. Vol. 7, No. 15, dated 1920 (Oversize-folder 1)
    Russia (an angry bear) uses a bayonet to poke Civilization (a beehive) while the rest of Europe watches.
  - Let's Judge for Ourselves. Vol. 7, No. 17, dated 1920 (Oversize-folder 2)
    Presidential candidates James M. Cox and Warren G. Harding whitewash and mud-sling a book, representing the League of Nations.
  - The Flying Wedge! Vol. 7, No. 19, dated 1920 (Oversize-folder 2)
    Democrats and Republicans play football, with the League of Nations serving as the ball.
  - Coal, Coal, Who's Got the Coal? Vol. 7, No. 20, dated 1920 (Oversize-folder 2)
    The Coal Trust turns away the American general public while selling at a higher rate to coal-starved Europe.
  - The Home Stretch! Vol. 7, No. 21, dated 1920 (Oversize-folder 2)
    At the races, Democratic presidential candidate James M. Cox (on his donkey-pulled chariot) is shown losing to Republican candidate Warren G. Harding (on his elephant).
  - Those Election Bets! Vol. 7, No. 22, dated 1920 (Oversize-folder 2)
    Americans parade with their winning and losing bets following the presidential election.
  - The Pied Piper! Vol. 7, No. 36, dated 1921 (Oversize-folder 2)
    German war payments flood towards France and England, who say that it is not enough.
  - Signs of Spring. Vol. 7, No. 41, dated 1921 (Oversize-folder 2)
    A family prepares for warmer weather and exhibits signs of spring fever.